I’m going to ask you about these words now.
You’ve mentioned one already. Maorach.
That was just a general name for shellfish?
That’s right.
That was quite commonly used?
Aye, it was that.
That didn’t apply to any specific types of shellfish?
No, no I think all shellfish was known as maorach.
Now, [there are/?] two words I’m quite interested in,
[skelf/?] and [skleef/?].
Skelf?
Are you familiar with both of these words?
Well, a skelf. I’ve heard of a skelf.
It’s only connected with wood as far as I know.
A skelf is just a paring of the wood you see.
Any sharp thing coming against the wood
and you just take a skelf off it, you see.
You haven’t heard of [skleef/?]?
No.
I understand that means a notch in a rock.
[Skleef/?]. I think it possibly comes from the same Gaelic word as ‘skelf’.
… I've never heard it referred to as [skleef/?] at all.
I heard it in Tarbert in Carradale, you know.
I wasn’t sure what it was.
They’re different you see.
There’s more Gaelic up that ways.
Now …
there’s a word that I’ve heard is used on board the skiffs
when they would be paring wood shavings to kindle a fire.
There’s a name for these shavings.
Aye, what’s this?
Sgla. Aah, aye, it starts with an ‘s’ too.
[Slisheams/?]?
[Sliseag/?], [sliseag/?], [sliseags/?].
That’s right, [sliseags/?].
Now …
did you use the word [spleiter/?]? [Spleiter/?].
Many a time.
What was that?
[XX] went through a tub of water
and went [spleitering/?] up the way.
[XX] is called an awful [spleiter/?].
Now there was a word …
that was, I think, connected with superstition to a certain extent.
It was used about an unlucky person aboard a boat
that would be called a certain name.
Oh well now, I knew that.
Oh dear goodness.
Oh, I should have come here about 20 year ago.
Was it a bòcan?
A bòcan - that’s correct. A bòcan.
It was a word that was very commonly used in fishing.
What type of people would it apply to?
Just anyone who was unlucky.
Or else maybe some fella coming off for the night you see
and getting no herring and all the rest getting some.
That’s the word you would say, the expression you would … you're a bòcan.
Don't you come oot to [XX].
If I could ask you about some words for fish.
Now, there’s quite a range of words used
for various stages of the saithe and its development.
Can you remember some of these for the smaller stuff?
Cuddies.
And there’s one for the …
The glaisean
[Kleshin/?].
And now there’s a word that’s used.
It’s more used in Tarbert. Piuchdaidh.
Piuchdaidh
Now, I thinks that’s …
Piuchdaidh that’s just-  you can say that piuchdaidh is a glaisean.
Now was that used in Campbeltown or Dalintober?
Och aye, aye aye.
The glaisean …
the glaisean was supposed to be
the proper name of it, you see.
They are both Gaelic names.
Are they?
Oh well, I suppose any of them will do.
The biggest stage was - can you remember that? The big …
The stainler?
The stainler, aye.
Now the spotted dogfish had a name.
The Gaelic name for that was used too.
The spotted dogfish. Och.
Was that the mùrlach?
Aye, it's the mùrlach but is that the spotted dogfish?
Aye.
Aye, the mùrlach.
It’s the one without the [XX].
That's right, aye.
You could scrub your -
scrub the floor with the [XX] back.
It was as rough as a, as a,
it was as rough on the back as a scrubbing brush.
Would you skin it first or just let it dry out?
No, no, just …
What, do you mean for scrubbing?
Aye
Oh no, just catch the old dead fish.
But what would you dae for eating it?
Eh? We weren’t going to eat it.
It was just there, it would never have been ate.
[...] dogfish.
Now there was a Gaelic word used there for the gurnard?
The gurnard?
No. I’m beat here.
The oudan, an oudan
That’s correct, that’s correct aye.
Aye, you know the name.
Are you familiar with the word cleek?
Aye.
What senses of the word are you familiar with?
A hook.
Would a hook actually be called a cleek?
Aye, well you see when we used to play the …
play the cleek it was just a round ring,
iron ring and the cleek, the cleek …
it propelled the ring along the street as far as you’d like to go.
The actual instrument for moving the wheel to go round.
Was there actually a hook on it?
Aye, it is a hook. It’s a solid thing.
It’s actually hooked on to the wheel?
Is it actually hooked onto the wheel?
No, no. It was just, you birl your wheel first.
It's only just a light iron ring
and when you just, when you get it going,
just get your cleek in at the back of it.
Aye, I’m too, I’m too young to know that.
I know about the cleek right enough. [XX]
It used to be, it used to be an annual game.
[...]
You'd have the cleek one time, one year,
one part of the year and you’d have the jarries the other part of the year.
You know the jarries?
Marbles.
That’s right, that’s right.
You had all the old-fashioned names.
Now just two or three more here.
I’ll let you by.
I’ll surely manage to squeeze through if I don’t trample your …
Now I don’t know if this word has come in
more into use recently or whether it was used a lot in your day.
It was the word for the wee scallops - the queen scallops.
The queen - queenies? Aye.
No, it never was used,
would never have been used in my day.
What was it they called them then?
Creachans?
Well, no. No, the creachans is …
the creachans only came into
to my vocabulary about 10 years ago.
I suspected that.
I think that’s more a Tarbert word or a…
when they started fishing for them.
That’s right, aye.
I don’t remember what the…
what we used to call them.
It used to be very thick up at Skippinish Bay there.
Someone was getting the fill of the ring net of them.
And maybe a fella would shout to you ‘What did you get there?’
Instead of…
instead of calling them … what did you call them?
Creachans.
Creachans,  we’d tell them …
It wisnae clams, no?
No, no clams is a bigger shellfish.
Strange the way it goes away out of your mind.
Maybe it will come back to you, later maybe.
Aye, afore you’re halfway out the door there it might, eh.
Now there was a wee creature which resembled the porpoise.
Is there a name in that?
I know what you’re asking but I can’t remember.
You just …
Is it a pulag?
Pollag! Pollag! The pollag!
Now was that a porpoise?
I think so, I think it was a younger porpoise.
Of course they were always on their own.
You see you get them especially around about the island there, [Devar?/] Island.
And then you might not see one again till you’re on the Isle of Ross.
They’re never in twos and threes
as you see with the porpoises.
There’s half a dozen at a time.
Now, we were speaking about shellfish.
There are some specific names for shellfish.
Can you remember any of these … local names?
Spute fish - is that …?
I think that's just spout fish.
There are one or two here.
The clappy dubh, are you familiar with that?
Aye, that’s a bigger mussel, the cloopy dubh.
You got them doon there about Achnan[XX].
Used to use them for bait.
Baiting lines?
Aye.
Would you gather them or dredge them up?
Eh?
Would you dredge them up or would you gather them by hand?
No, you dredged them up.
I mean you’re working out in maybe ten or a
dozen fathom of water [before you could get them/?].
Did you ever hear of [saul dubh/?]?
[Saul dubh/?], aye.
What was that?
Well, that's feeding for the fish.
Did you have any idea what that meant? Did anybody ever …
[Saul dubh?/]?
Aye … can you give an explanation of that?
I think it was always [saul dubh/?] I heard them referred to.
It’s big something isn’t it?
Eh, well the …
[Saul dubh/?]
Well, dubh is black.
Oh, black, aye.
The Tarbert ones say it’s black eyes but the
meaning you would expect would be black seed, like sile, seed.
I think it possibly comes from the same word.
You’re familiar with sile too?
Aye, aye.
What … what did that eh …?
It’s young herring.
Young herring.
A-ha.
Was there any other young fish that called by that name?
That was called by that name?
Not that I know of, no.
Now, there’s two or three here.
Now the winkie was called a winkie here, but
was there any other name for it you heard of?
Aye, when I went to the fishing at first.
Do you take sugar?
Eh, aye please.
How much? Two?
Is it a wee cup?
Aye, they’re no very big.
Eh, could I have one please.
One? Just one?
One will be fine thanks.
We’re just about finished, en. [XX]
When I went fishing first it was the [learie/?].
The [learie/?]?
You didna hear of stuthaidh?
Stuthaidh - aye.
That wasn’t …
No they didn’t call it that.
That was put on to the lines. Aye.
Did they use that in Campbeltown,
Stuthaidh. That word?
Och aye, you’d hear an odd fella refer to it as stuthaidh.
It wasn’t in general use you know.
Was that just a buoy?
It was a buoy with corks on it and maybe
if you were on the lines, there were a flag on it, you see.
That’s quite interesting.
Eh?
I wonder if these men that were using that word were Gaelic speakers?
Or came off a Gaelic …
Och no, I don't think so.
Can you remember any of the men?
They might eventually … no, no.
What was that you said there?
Eh, stuthaidh.
Aye.
No, I don’t think any of them’s Gaelic speakers.
Now there’s another word eh …
was used for the,
for a boat hook … it was a,
a pole with a wooden cross [piece on the end/?].
What was the name for that?
Was that the …?
Skiddaw.
Now, was that the only device which was called with that name?
Was there anything else called that name?
No. I can’t think.
No, the skiddaw … that’s what you went for, the …
There you are. Are you right?
Thank you.
I didn’t know whether to feed you up. [XX]
There’s plenty mair, [Annie/?], aren’t there.
[Dods/?] usually takes two, sometimes three. [XX] …
Do you know the word [sgeochal/?]?
[Sgeochal/?]?
Aye, sgeochal.
Here you are. [Have a wee biscuit/?]
One will be fine. Thank you.
No, [sgeochal/?].
Oh, God [XX] … my feet’s … aye in the road.
[Sgeochal/?], let me think.
Margaret, have you heard that …
What’s that?
The word [sgeochal/?]?
[Sgeochal/?] [XX]
Someone [sgeochaling/?], clearing his throat.
Now there’s a name for that now.
No, it’s not [sgeochal/?].
No,  I think there’s a name for that right enough.
[Did you/?] feed enough?
I’m fine aye.
[Neilogan/?]
What?
No, it’s a word I’ve never heard used very much.
I believe I’ve heard it right enough I think and I canna,
I canna think what it’s referred to at all.
It’s just a …
a word I’ve only heard the one person [speaking about/?].
I don’t, I don’t even know if it’s Gaelic or not.
I’m just wondering.
No.
Och, it’s Gaelic [XX]- if it is a word.
Gaelic.
[XX] Just, just the final two words here.
They both … meant a light breeze of wind.
Eh?
A light breeze of wind.
Can you remember any words for a light breeze of wind?
[Just an air/?]
Did you hear of a sar?
Sar? Aye.
Sar, aye, sar. [...]
An air of wind and a sar of wind.
Was there any difference between the two?
An air and a sar.
They were just the same thing.
Just a light, a light breeze?
Aye, a light breeze.
Very, very light.
Now there’s a word up in Tarbert, flan.
That’s the same.
Do they use that in Campbeltown too?
Hmm, yes, just a flan.
That’s fine.
God, did you never hear tell of burgoo?
No, no, no, no. What does it mean?
Porridge!
Aye.
I never heard that, no.
There was a man that worked at [Strathend/?] told me that.
He worked on a farm. Galbraith, he was Davy Galbraith.
[We just met in the café/?] and I was asking him if there,
if there was a country word for [bringing in water/?].
Aha.
Did you ever …
are you familiar with any word used in
the country farms for [drawing/?] in water?
No, I was only a wee lassie.
I don’t think I was five or so.
Oh well.
I wouldn’t know.
Then we came into the town.
What connection did you hear burgoo?
It’s because that’s …
many a time I heard porridge being referred to as burgoo.
Many a time.
Aboard the, the boats?
Aye, and in the hoose.
In the hoose, aye.
Remember they used to [take/?] porridge [or oats/?]
or what was they had in the countryside in olden times.
The pot used to go on the table
and they would all [spoon/?] it out the pot.
What was that?
Was it soup or porridge?
It was porridge as far as I knew, or burgoo if you like.
All sitting round the table with a bit pot in the middle of the table
and just taking spoonfuls out of the pot, you know.
Some life!
No, that was …
No.
I think they did all their cooking over an open fire too.
That’s right, over an open fire.
That’s right, aye.
What was the arrangement for cooking?
I don’t know how they, how they …
Of course we should know that-[XX] my mother …
it was an open fire my mother had.
You see when the fire was open
they had a thing, a ring, solid ring …
That was the ranges.
This was an open fire before that.
Aye, well with an open fire too.
You just put it [into an open/?] [XX]
alongside the edge of the fire and it swung right oot on the top of the fire.
You could swirl it right round …
and you put your pot on the top of the [sling/?] and let it boil away.
There was a name.
What did you ca’ that?
Well I know when we had the open fire there were two bits,
one on each side of the fire, the big fire in the middle.
You just put your pot at the side of the fire and […].
Or if you were [any/?] in a hurry you put it on top of the fire.
And you had a bar up, well up, up the chimney
and you had a chain hooked on to that bar,
with a hook in the bottom of the chain
and that hooked on to the handle of the pot.
Now there was a name in that bar.
Can you remember it?
Aye, I canna mind about that wee thing.
The [swee/?]?
It might have been that thing, that thing that you out the pots on,
you know that that wee twisted round [bit/?] …
I can’t remember.
And then the gas rings came in.
[XX]
It we was very …
Now …
you didna …
cut peats at all? Was it coal?
No, it was coal we burned really.
We didn’t get …
there weren’t many trees, you see. We never got … logs.
Well, I’ll tell you what,
they used to go over with the boat, over to Auchterferry
and there was great wood came in there on the shore
and they used to fill the boat with that and take it home
and saw it up and we used that.
And then there were whins at [Gruan na Creig/?] and in the [Garbost/?]
and the [Barr/?]
so sometimes they were as thick as that,
the whins so they were beautiful.
We used to burn them you see and then they were ready for …
you burned them when they got withered
and they were ready for to going in and you kindled your fire with that.
My mother used to bake,
with those whins you know - they made a lovely fire for baking.
That would be the actual stems you would be using?
Yes, that’s right.
Oh, the jaggy bits were terrible. We left them.
Would you just cut these with an axe or …
Yes, they were very easy broken.
Sometimes you broke them with your knees just or broke them with your hand.
But of course if there were thicker ones you cut them with an axe.
There was always plenty of instruments like that about the place.
Would that be the … the job of the children?
Pardon?
Would it [have been/?] the children’s job?
Yes, yes. We used to always go.
And then the burning of the heather … the heather when it was burned -
they called it in the Gaelic falaisg.
Falaisg?
And it was very thin of course,
wee thin bits but oh it was lovely for kindling a fire.
We never needed to be without it.
There was a peat moss up at the end of the Craig.
They called it peat moss but it was under water.
But there must have been peat dug there once upon a time
because it was quite peaty at the side.
But I don’t mind of our folk ever cutting peat really.
Did they ever …?
You know that gentleman I was on about.
Well he said that,
you know [XX] down the road,
down [XX] Street …
there’s a place there.
Well he said that was the Gaelic word for whelks.
Oh, I see.
[XX] That was what he said.
Well, might be right enough.
And they used to go down and fill their boats down there
and then that paid the rent for the year or what ever way they wanted to do these…
[XX] Well he said … that’s what he told me,
that [peacach/?] was the Gaelic word for [whelks/?].
Whether that’s true, I don't know.
Sgadan [naturally/?] of course that’s the Gaelic for herring.
But what do they call the rest of the fish I don’t know.
Mackerel and whitings and haddocks and …?
Reannach, in Tarbert anyway, reannach, mackerel.
Mackerel.
Well, a gobag was a dogfish.
A dogfish, it was a dogfish right enough.
And a mùrlach too.
And a piocach, the piocach of course,
the piocach was the, the saithe.
The saithe. Aye, that’s right.
That seems to be the word they use it Tarbert.
But doon this way, it’s more glaisean.
Aye, glaisean aye.
The glaisean yes, that’s right, yes.
We call the glaisean, did we call …?
No, we called it [stemlach/?]. But was that the glaisean.
I think that was the big ones
That was the big ones, aye. The big ones.
They’re lovely, salted.
These … these saithe you salted, would they …
would they be caught by hand lines?
The saithe.
No, no the rod.
The rods.
We used the rods.
Would that just be from the rocks?
You were out on the loch and you rowed all the time,
and you drew it after you, you see,
and then you caught them.
And oh what a job it used to be taking them in.
We used to … we weren’t good at taking them in, that’s us as young folk.
We used to swing them round our heads, you know,
and hitting somebody in the face.
You had a board across the stern, you see, with a slot.
You know, two boards nailed with a slot
and the rod went in there, spread out.
That was a [sgathach/?], wasn’t it?
That’s right, yes.
That was a [sgathach/?] they called that boat
and you didn’t get them just till the [dusk/?] came in
and then you wouldn’t get one and then they would just come up
when the [dusk/?] came in. You could follow them …
Yes, they just rowed very slowly through the [XX].
[XX] and then take them in.
Yes.
You mentioned too that the fishermen used to go for coals.
Yes [XX]
they went to Greenock for coal
with a fishing [skift/?]
and they took so many tonne- I don't know how many tonne it would be.
And then of course they couldn’t,
of course they couldn’t get the fishing [skift/?] in
near the shore because it ebbed up a good bit.
You know, the ebb went out and …
but when it was high water and that they took it in pretty near
and then of course they just carried it in bags or in a barra,
you know, into the place.
Of course it was never put indoors - it was just left in a place.
We called it the cùlag,
I don’t know what that means really.
It’s a Gaelic name
but it was this place at the byre and you just emptied it in there.
And the coal was beautiful …
oh it was so cheap too
and it was glossy, thon glossy coal.
We had a well. The well was beautiful.
It was as cold in summer as it was in the winter,
with the spring just coming from the hill.
And we cleaned that well-
we had to clean it regular
and we put those white chuckie stones, as they call it,
in the bottom of the well
and we would catch a trout in the burn and put it in to keep it clean.
It would eat up all the weeds and things.
That’s what we did.
That trout would be there all year?
It went round all the time, it lived there all the time.
It was wonderful really.
And then there was always a wee outlet for the water to go very slowly,
you know, in case the water might get sort of stagnant.
But it never did of course.
Was that well actually … would it be … was it bricked?
No, it was just … it just seemed to be stones right around it.
[There were/?] some flagstones at the side, you bent down and then you carried …
it was stoups you had.
Did you hear of the stoups?
Stoup? Stoup? [Oh aye/?]
They’re in Auchindrain - they’re in Auchindrain Museum I think our stoups,
at [Silvercraig/?] I think Miss Campbell [Kilberry/?] came down
so I think May gave her the stoups.
It was a wooden … they made the stoups too of course, the men.
It was wooden … it was just round … they were round and wooden.
They were that size
and then there was just a handle.
The handle was fitted into each side.
But my goodness when you went to carry you had to take two
to balance yourself coming from the water.
Oh, it was, it was really great.
That was the stoups.
Now I asked you about the word for wood shavings.
… Sliseags?
That was used only in connection with kindling the fire?
[...]
and you broke it off into sliseags for starting the fire.
That was the only use of the word?
Aye, that was all […], sliseags.
Now, you mentioned [screenge/?] net too.
[Screenge/?]?
Was that an old one?
No, well no, no.
That was when they started with those ground nets for [lèabag/?],
for flounders.
They called it a screenge.
That was later days.
A screenge net - it originally came from the East Coast.
Just a ground net.
That’s interesting …
I’ve come across the word in connection with the West Highlands.
It was used for a wee trawl net, a wee ring net.
They used to haul them to the shore.
But eh … that seems to be a … a recent …
Screenge is a different thing a’ the gether.
But a [ballicrubach/?]
I was going to come to that word. Aye …
The [wee/?] net.
You know, they [would get tied up/?], you know.
A [XX] [newton/?] would tie up the torn butt
with the [XX] butt [XX] [crubble/?] net
Cupple net?
Crubble net.
[Crùbach/?] [XX]
Whatever way they joined the two [XX] a [ballicrubach/?].
Very [friendly/?]  Gaelic, very old Gaelic.
That’s what [they did/?], a [ballicrubach/?].
Did [everybody/?] apply that word to just a wee ring net reduced in size?
When they were [teeing/?] the net
we would telling them to make a [ballicrubach/?].
And they would work away at it.
So that was the application of the word?
Aye [...]
Now … I asked you before …
Well, but [...] tied up [the torn/?] [XX] [ballicrubach/?].
Was the word sùgan ever used in that context? [XX]
Sùgan?
Sùgan
Och, aye. They aye used the sùgan
when they got a net fairly heavy.
They made a bunch of the net,
a sùgan and tied it to [it/?] with a rope on to the [gunnel/?].
That was keeping the whole [of the weight/?] away from the herring.
That was a sùgan.
That’s the only use that word had?
Aye. That’s the only use it was [after/?], sùgan just,
keeping the herring up.
That was tied, the boat was [XX],
the rest was heaving up against that sùgan.
You see that’s for sticking up [XX] a big bunch [XX] of leaves in the net,
tied round with a rope
and the last of the stringer
and then they would drag the herring up to the…
that was never touched until the net was empty.
Sùgan. [...] That was the sùgan.
Now there’s an expression here …
I read …
I think I read of this in connection with Loch Fyne fishing.
I don’t know whether you’re familiar with it - [salachar iasg/?],
[salachar iasg/?] -
the herring [dirt/?] I think would be the definition.
Did you ever hear of that? …
No?
What did you call it again?
[Salachar iasg/?], [salachar iasg/?]
No, I never heard about that.
It was aye the herring [dirt/?].
Just the [dirt/?] they called it?
The herring [dirt/?].
You would get it together on the tides.
No, I never heard that expression.
Now …
Of course, old men might use it. [XX]
This may have been up about Minard and towards the north.
I don’t think it …
it wasn’t mentioned in connection with Tarbert, it was further north.
It was maybe a word that was peculiar there, a term that was peculiar there.
Eh?
I think it …
I think it probably was used further north - Loch Fyne,
up at Minard and Furnace and these places.
There was a book about Loch Fyneside I read it in but
Tarbert wasn’t included in the area the book was covering …
so maybe it wasn’t known down here.
I’ve never heard of it.
If I could come on here to the Gaelic word for cod.
Was there a word here?
What?
For a cod fish. A cod.
Aye,
they had the wee half fish.
They had names for the big ones and the wee half ones.
[Coddlings/?].
What’s this now [...]
Aye.
My mind certainly is fuzzy.
It wasn’t bodach-ruadh, was it?
Eh?
Bodach-ruadh.
No, that was the [XX] … Bodach-ruadh? [XX].
They used to call them reddy coloured right enough.
Now, that was used in …
No, but … [XX]
Where?
They used that in South Kintyre for the wee kind of red rock cod.
Called them a bodach-ruadh.
But that wasn’t used here?
Rock cod?
There was a name for the cod,
the smaller ones but I just canna get it …
you know the half ones, no’ the big cod but what they got in their [XX].
It will maybe be come to you.
[...] bodach-ruadh.
Rock cod.
The lumps of cod they [called/?] [XX].
Geàrr-bhodach, no?
What was that? Geàrr-bhodach?
Geàrr-bhodach.
That was the kind of half size cod- geàrr-bhodach.
You know, between the big cod and the wee ones.
Geàrr-bhodach but I couldn’t gie you the pronunciation of it or what it means.
Geàrr-bhodach. You know, the cod, the half-sized cod. […].
Geàrr-bhodach.
Now, was there a …
a Gaelic word for mealing water? The drink.
Mealing water?
Aye …
I think it’s different.
There were some of them called it the [gruel/?].
You’d put in a couple of neeffels of water in the can.
Couple of neeffers? What’s a neeffer?
A neeffel, for your [hand/?]
A neeffel?
For your [hand/?] …
mealing water they called it.
Gruel, I think that’s a …
The gruel, that’s an English name.
That was heated though, the gruel.
But the mealing water,
I canna mind now but they had another name for it.
It was just [XX] the [XX] water.
The Campeltown fishermen called it maorach, which is the same …
Maorach?
… which is the same name as the shellfish.
Oh, that’s [XX]. Aye, that’s right.
The [XX] men had a name but I canna mind.
The gruel was there.
The mealing water [was boiled/?].
Like porridge practically.
Like porridge.
That was the gruel but
the mealing water was as often
the mealing waters they called it.
But there was this other name now, I canna get it.
It wasn’t stiùrag or anything like that?
Stiùrag.
Well, it could be.
I canna …
that was thin thin mealing water - [storrait/?] or stiùrag.
[A fella now/?] [XX], he was making porridge water [XX]
and that was what he came oot [XX]
‘You’re putting too much meal in the pot.’
‘Now, none of your damn stiùrag here’, he said
and I kept mind then of stiùrag.
But that’s what he alluded to, the porridge.
It must have been watery porridge.
‘None of your damn stiùrag here’ he said.
He was the cook making the porridge.
Now, that’s why I kept mind of that.
He was the name of Cameron. [Sgiathag/?] we called him.
[Sgiathag/?]?
Aye. Not from the north.
Well, he was [...] but he was married in […].
‘Damn it, you’re putting too much meal in the pot.’
‘None of your damn stiùrag here’, he said.
I’ve kept mind this…
He was from the north, that man?
No, when he was in the north.
Oh, when he was in the north, I see, aye.
He was really a Tarbert man but he got married up there and stayed.
He bought a boat in Campbeltown [XX].
I can’t remember the name of the boat, a big clinker boat.
The memory, aye.
I canna mind, a big clinker [XX].
There’s just one more word there.
You mentioned a word …
Gaelic word for the state of drunkenness.
Drunkenness? Aye.
This is the last time I was in …
I think we were going through a …
compiling a list of words,
the different words and expressions that were used …
I think it was a …
[...]
I think it was a word the old men used.
Drunk. Mortal.
I think that’s English, mortal, aye.
Mortal.
Well … [XX].
That was the Gaelic
that you were drunk or if you [were with/?] a drink.
Do you know that one?
What was the, what was that one again?
[Ainnear/?], [ainneir/?].
I don’t know how you would write it.
That may have been the one.
It could have been it …
I think that’s everything.
No, I can’t think of anything else.
I think that’s maybe it, aye.
[Annear/?], [annar/?].
I’ll need to watch my time with this bus. Quarter to.
[You better not miss your bus/?].
[XX] date of birth, Carrie … Caroline … Carrie.
Ask you the year?
No, what year were you born?
What’s your … when’s your birthday, Car.
20th August
What year?
1904. That was in Dalantober.
Well, if you could just …
anyone that can add anything, just join in.
[Railleach/?],  did you hear that word?
You what?
[Railleach/?]
Aye.
Aye, what did that describe?
I would say it was kind of rough.
[Railleach/?] …
Well I’ve heard of it [XX]
Now, what …
what circumstances would that be applied?
Well, to me anybody kind of tough or rough speaking.
A rough family.
Oh weren’t they awful [railleach/?]
Or coming off a rough kind of family.
Maybe I’m making a mistake.
No, it seems to be …
it seems to be more so often applied to the weather.
The weather?
Aye.
Aye, well it could be rough weather.
It could be rough [anything/?].
You could even say that it was a [railleach/?] day or something
[XX] at that time of [year/?].
Have you heard that expression?
[...]
No, but I’ve heard [railleach/?]
Just applied to …
It’s awful [railleach/?] Coarse, I would say.
That can apply to almost anything?
Aye, could do.
Have you heard of a …
a word for left-handed? Or a left-handed [person/?]
[Cayd-i-chur/?] [Cayd-i-chur/?]
Is there another name?
Is there no’?
Corrie-handed.
Aye, corrie-handed. That’s right
[Cayd-i-chur/?] [Cayd-i-chur/?]
I thought there was another [though/?].
I’m no’ sure.
You don’t hear that word used now, no?
No, no you don’t. Corrie-fisted [XX].
Aye, corrie-fisted.
Are you familiar with the word sgliùrach?
I’ve heard of …
Sgiùrach or sgliùrach?
Sgliùrach.
No, I’ve never heard of that. Did you?
No, no.
Now, what was that?
I think I have. It’s no’ a Campbeltown word.
Is it the Gaelic? Sgliùrach.
Aye, it’s used in Campbeltwon.
It’s applies to part of a woman …
a slovenly woman … or a useless person.
No.
Never heard the expression.
I maybe saw it in your Gaelic book wi’ the words.
[Jean/?], had a book wi’ Gaelic words.
Mind you were learning Gaelic.
Are ye … familiar with the word spuidsear? A spuidsear.
It’s a bailing-dish. It’s used more in the fishing right enough.
No, never heard it. Spuidsear.
Did you ever hear a word for a net mender …
even the women in the factories?
No.
Cliùcairs. No? Cliùcairs.
Cliùcairs? Cliùcairs? [XX]
The word [skaivin/?]
No.
[Skaivin?/]?
It’s similar to skite.
Skate, no?
No, it’s [skaivin/?], skimming.
And then there’s [skaver/?].
[Skavers/?]
Whit’s that?
Well, I don’t know but there’s a fisherman …
Oh, aye [XX] [Matheson/?]. Aye, well.
[Skavers/?].
Nicknames often don’t …
Do they no’ come into it?
Well they sometimes don’t mean anything …
very much or the meaning …
the meaning is lost.
What about the word [droud/?] …
[Droud/?]?
A [droud/?].
No. No.
Or a glaimh?
For a glutton.
Glutton?
Oh, a glutton.
Glutton’s common.
No, but glaimh for a glutton,
used … applied to a glutton.
No, I never heard.
Now, you mentioned [misleach/?].
What was your explanation o’ that?
A [misleach/?]?
A mixture. All mixed up.
Anything … a [misleach/?], aye.
If there was a lot of anything all mixed up you would say ‘Oh, what a [misleach/?]’.
Does that apply to food?
Aye, anything.
Or a mess, even?
Just interested in the applications of the word.
Can you remember any instances that you used it …
any examples of it.
Well, if you were looking at anything that was all mixed up-
food or anything,
you would say ‘Oh, what a [miseach/?]’.
Is that [miseach/?] or [misleach/?]?
[Miseach/?], [miseach/?], a [misleach/?], a [misleach/?].
A [misleach/?]?
No, a [miseach/?]
A [miseach?/]?
It’s a [miseach/?].
A [miseach/?]. Oh, well.
It’s no’ [misleach/?], it’s [miseach/?]. A [miseach/?].
You know a wee bit of your Gaelic, eh.
I’m not sure whether it’s Gaelic. It might be.
I think it will be.
And you mentioned another …
What did I mention?
About spreading.
How did I … what was that?
Like, the spreading?
Aye?
[Smùrach/?].
Oh, a [smeurach/?].
Put a wee [smeurach/?] on.
Put a wee [smeurach/?] of butter …
If you’re spreading butter or anything like that.
A wee [smeurach/?].
Spreading jam.
That might nae be Gaelic,
it might just be the English word ‘smear’ wi’ the Gaelic suffix.
Aye, it might right enough. It might not be the true Gaelic.
It may be. [Smeurach/?] That’s just like a …
Just a …
Spread
Just a, just put a wee [smeurach/?] on.
I’ve never heard of it before.
Did ye no’?
No.
Was that only used in connection with spreading butter?
Aye, or anything … jam or anything.
Anything like that on the table.
Anything you could …
And you mentioned another one,
meaning a … but I’ll mention the word- thruither.
Thruither?
Thruither.
Aye.
Aye, that’s common enough for a carry on.
But he’s got another… are you thinking on another word?
No, that’s one of the … no, no
Somebody that’s just full of life and carry on.
Aye, thruther. Aye.
Just canna sit at peace.
Full of, you know.
They’re full of nonsense but nothing … nothing behind it.
Kind of tomboy.
But nothing behind it.
You didn’t hear that applied in any other sense?
No.
One of the definitions is anything higglety pigglety or,
you know, confusion.
No, no’ really.
Who’s that person or if you’re speaking about a kiddie that’s aye on the go.
[...]
Now you didn’t hear,
perhaps any of the older fishermen,
use another word for herring?
Herring?
No’ really.
You didn’t hear sgadan?
Aye. I’ve heard that, aye.
[XX] How long ago was that?
How long ago?
Was that …?
Well, it must be when I was younger.
Your father would be at the fishing.
Sgadan. Sgadan. Do they mean that they’re wee?
No, no.
[Sgadish/?]
No, no sgadan, sgadan, the Gaelic for herring.
Is it?
I thought it meant if they were sgadan,
I thought really that they meant wee.
No [XX] What [XX] Was that a general one?
Was it generally used? Did you hear it often?
Did they no’ used to say ‘Had you have anything …’
'Och, aye sgadan'. You know if …
You’re not thinking of [sgadach/?]?
No, no, no. Sgadan.
‘Oh, just a sgadan.’
I thought that was kind of saying.
Did your father use that?
Aye, I’ve heard him speaking about sgadan.
… that you had wi’ …
Och, aye. Oh, aye- that’s the [sgana/?].
I’d just be interested to know how commonly used it was in Campbeltown and [Tarbert/?].
You didn’t hear of a [torgeen/?] or a [torrigan/?]?
[XX] And what does that mean? Does that mean tomboy or …?
No.
[Torigeen/?]?
It’s mainly a fishing term but I believe that it can also be used [tae/?] a
bandage. A [torgeen/?].
No.
God, it’s great the words that was used in these days.
Och. Aye, and you never thought.
What about skelf?
[Likes/?] of a skelf in your finger, is it?
A splint, a wee splinter.
Splint.
Did you hear another word similar to that?
Staff.
Skleef?
No. Skleef.
No. No, I never heard that.
A skleef in a rock.
A crevice in a rock.
Another one you mentioned is sar. What was a sar?
A sar? A light wind.
A wee sar coming in from the sea.
I’ve heard Duncan [XX] saying that. [A sar/?]. Funny enough …
A light wind. A light wind.
[XX] … when he was with Gaimler at the fishing.
He used to say, you know when he was speaking,
he used to say there was a sar. Aye, I heard that.
I’m sure on many’s a, on a warm day we used to say
‘Oh I wish a wee sar would get out.'
We would be sitting in Strathend and that. A wee breeze.
You didn’t hear a word flan.
[Flan/?]? Not except for when you’re baking.
No, this was …
it had the same meaning as sar.
Was it?
Not many people …
I think there was only one person in Campbeltown that recognised it.
[XX] it was used in the 1920s and 30s […].
What about [muillidh?] or [muilleans/?]
The name’s kind of familiar. [Muilleans/?]
Crumbs.
Milleans.
It’s not [muilleans/?] I heard, it was mil …
look at the milleans you’ve made.
It was never [muilleans/?] for … wi’ us.
I assure you we aye said ‘Look at the milleans you’ve left’.
You know, the wee ones making a mess.
Oddly enough I was up in Tarbert on Friday and wasn’t there an old man there.
[I was recording him/?] and that was the word he used- milleans.
Anything that goes into dust.
Aye, that’s right, aye.
Milleans.
That’s quite a common word in your [XX]?
Oh, aye. Aye, it’s quite common.
You didn’t hear of a [kilogie/?]?
A kilogie? Aye, I’ve heard of it.
Do they … there’s another word that came after that.
A kilogie wheat. A linnet.
Aye, a kilogie linnet.
There was a second then I was saying no, it’s no’ that.
Have you no idea what a kilogie was?
No.
[XX]
Would it be wild? No?
No, I’m told that it’s a stove used in stills and
a kilogie linnet was a person that was fond of the heat.
He would be up against it whenever there was heat.
The linnet would be a kilogie.
Kilogie. Oh, I’ve heard o that.
What about [spleiter/?]?
Och, aye.
What’s a [spleiter/?]?
A splash.
Aye, a splash.
Of water or anything.
A spleiter. A spleiter.
We even use that yet.
‘Don’t spleiter.’
‘Don’t splieter’. So you do.
That’s no’ Gaelic, no?
Aye
Is it?
Spleiter.
Gosh, we’re using Gaelic words and we don’t …
Oh, I’ve said on many’s a day
‘Oh, you’ve spleitered that all over the place'.
Many’s a time I’ve said that.
Aye, same here.
Aye and there’s another word splooter.
Splooter?
Aye, I’ve heard of that.
That’s probably …
the two are probably connected.
Well, the two might be meaning the same thing, I would think.
Well that’s the point, did they mean the same thing?
Well … aye, I think it would.
Aye, but they weren’t used differently?
If you were spilling anything, you would say ‘Oh, what a splooter’.
[XX] Would you say splootering? ‘Stop your splootering.’
Aye.
Well, probably …
It’s just connected with [spleiter/?].
Aye … it’s something similar.
What about [caointeachs/?]?
Oh, I heard of [caointeachs/?] long ago.
‘Sitting there like a [caointeach/?].’
What did that mean?
I don’t know really what that meant.
It meant something.
Is it no’ a bird?
No, no.
It’s wasn’t a bird.
Was it a light?
No.
A lot of folk used to use it in the eyes of a human being.
You know ‘You’re sitting there like a [caointeach/?].’
Oh, I thought it was the way you sat.
The position you were sitting in.
What was that about a human being?
No, it represents something …
A lot of folk used to say …
you know, maybe you’d be sitting at the fire and they’d say
‘You’re sitting there like a [caointeach/?].’
You know, to a human.
You wouldn’t say …
it wasn’t said to an animal or anything.
I’ve heard that expression
‘She’s sitting there like a [caointeach/?].’
I mean I’ve heard of it … so often.
It seems to apply to a human, you know.
You canna think of any other instances it was used in?
No, I just thought it was sitting [crouched/?] up.
Sitting like a [caointeach/?],
whatever a [caointeach/?] was.
But it applied really to a human,
it didn’t apply to an animal or anything like that, you know.
[...]
Years ago,
aye and if your dad was here he would mind it too,
what was a will-o’-the-wisp?
Did you ever hear of that?
Aye, I’ve heard of it, aye.
Oh, Duncan used to speak about it.
He’d say ‘Oh, aye there’s a light up there.
You could follow it and it would lead you.’
That was a will-o’-the-wisp.
Oh. Was it no’ a … ?
A light.
Was it no’ a flower or …
No, it’s a light.
It’s a light but I canna explain it [XX]
It kind of drew you
A light [XX] creature
It kind of drew you.
I believed … I believed in it when I was younger,
you know and I was kind of scared of it.
It was kind of frightening.
Will-o’-the-wisp
I bet, eh.
You can’t offer any explanations then?
You don’t remember any other instances it was used? [caointeach/?].
[XX] said it was often applied to a person
that was away on his own [XX]
A loner, a loner, aye.
Aye, he’s quite right, it is.
But, I mean it definitely …
it definitely … it means a human.
It doesn’t mean anything in the line of a …
of an animal or anything like that.
It really … it is said to a human.
A wee [caointeach/?].
It must have been wee because many’s a time we were called wee [caointeach/?].
Aye, but you didn’t understand why you were called it?
No, we just took it for granted, you know.
We just took it it was only a word, you know.
Is it a Gaelic?
Aye, it comes from Gaelic
And can you not get … can you get the meaning oot of it?
Well, in the … that …
Aye, you’re quite right there.
What about cac or cacaidh?
Cacaidh?
Shite …
is that not a colour?
Is that a colour you mean?
No, that’s Gaelic again just for the very word you used.
[...]
I can mind there were a man up in the next …
oh no, that’s … No [XX]
No, it’s no anything.
The next close and he was a traveller for Sloans in Glasgow.
He stayed next door to Sissy
and he used to come up to the club
and he actually liked the khaki shirts but would say
‘Oh aye, you want a khak-eye shirt?’
Khak-eye. Cock-eye.
You’ve got a right dose.
Was that … was that word cacaidh or cac.
Did you use hear it used as cac or just cacaidh?
Cacaidh. You’d often be cacaidh …
when you were wee.
Cac … cacaidh
Was there a word for the earwig?
A local word?
I’ll send you upstairs in a minute.
You’ll be wiping all this coughs off till he gets his …
Earwig.
No, I never, never heard of [XX]
No, wait a minute, I never …
I should know the other name. There is another name for it.
[Collag-lìn?]
[Collag-lìn/?] That’s right.
That’s what it is, aye.
How would you pronounce that?
[Collag-lìn/?] is how we said it when we were young.
I don’t know any other way. [Collag-lìn/?]
That’s the pronunciation, is it?
Is that thon wee beasts that used to [XX] And you’d get a wee crop …
You got them on a lot of flowers.
That’s right.
Dahlias.
We had to stop with growing a rose tree because the place was covered in …
Aye, even dahlias have hundreds and thousands in the summertime.
I was awfu fond of these …
Black …
you couldn’t take a bunch of dahlias in. [...]
That was the word you used …
That was the way we pronounced it - [collag-lìn?].
That was the word you used generally? You wouldn’t use earwig?
No, it wasn’t earwigs. It was only in later years it was earwigs.
Put in on till we hear it before Molly goes away. Molly’s going away.
[XX] what have you done to your ears? Mind they used to say.
And the word bus?
Aye, bus.
You’ve got a bus on your face.
That was somebody sitting very unpleasant.
You know, with their face tripping them.
Frown.
Is that Gaelic?
Aye.
Is it? Gosh.
Many’s time you would say ‘Look at her with the bus on her face’
That just means a pout or a sullen expression.
A dour expression, you know. No’ pleasant.
Now, mùgair?
[Mùgain/?], that’s a creeper.
[Mùgairean/?] bugger.
Now, are you saying [mùgain/?]?
[Mùgain’s/?] a plant.
No, [mùgairy/?].
[Mùgairean/?], is it? [Mùgairean/?].
It’s a person.
That applies to a person.
He’s a [mugairean/?] bugger.
That applies to a person, so it does.
No’ anyone.
What did that mean?
Dour.
[Mugairean/?].
Sort of creeping about on your own.
Mouching about and …
Now, glam.
Glam - that’s somebody getting a grip of you.
To grab.
Glam? Aye.
Aye, glammin’ you.
Somebody getting a grip of you.
That’s right.
He’s aye glammin’. I’ve heard it.
He’s aye glamming?
Aye. He’s a nuisance that fellow, he’s aye glammin’.
Something to that … you know you would say that.
I couldn’t be bothered with that fellow- he’s aye glammin’ at you.
It depends on who it is!
Christ, aye.
What about falachan?
That’s if you’ve got plenty of money.
If you fall into a falachan of money or falachan of anything.
That’s right, I’ve heard of that.
I wish there was a falachan would fall on the table noo.
I think it’s fallen gey weel.
There will be a tale to tell.
What about a word for a pimple or a spot?
Pluc.
A pluc. A pluc on your face …
a pluc somewhere else. Better no have said.
I could say a bit of poetry about that.
What was that?
‘A man was born in Kyle’
Oh, no it was a … it was.
‘grew a bile [boil] and when it burst, it burst in style’.
Where was it?
Eh? Where it shouldn’t have been?
Wi’ the man that got his bullet up his ….
There wasn’t a word for a teapot or a kettle?
A skill … a skillet. No.
That’s a pan.
What’s a skillet? That’s a pan.
A wee black basin, they used to cry them. [XX]
A teapot or a kettle?
A wee brown [XX] … I know a song about that.
I’m thinking of local … local words for it.
For a teapot?
No, I haven’t actually got anything on that.
Teapot.
[...]
You better watch your time, [Molly/?] I wouldn’t like you to miss …
When’s the bus coming?
When is it?
Ten to ten.
Ten to ten, aye.
The word [mùrlach/?]?
[Mùrlach/?]- that’s somebody neònach.
[Bùrlach/]?
[Mùrlach/?] Somebody from the country or something like that, it’s used.
Somebody that’s kind of …
Neònach … neònach …
That’s dressed kind of neònach is a [mùrlach/?].
In the feeing days they used to say
‘Oh the neònachs are all in the day.’
Them that was wanting a fee, ken.
Sort of country yokels
Hurry up and put it on till we hear it.
Gie’s a laugh.
… till I got that bottle from the doctor.
Did you hear that [XX]?
[XX] Aye … you’ve to take it with hot water.
She had a cough [XX] Aye, what …
Just a minute, please. Just a moment.
Right.
Aye, I’ve heard it as often.
I always used that word ‘Oh you [mùrlach/?]’ (for) years.
When I was only a wee lassie I heard that word used.
I mean I heard my mother using that word.
What eh … how would it be applied?
It was applied to regards a person … you know.
It was mostly applied to a man.
Was that a term of abuse?
Aye, it was … a lot of them …
it was applied to a lot of them the way they dressed.
Aye, [mùrlach/?]
That was when they were black or mucky or something.
Aye. Was it not?
No, it applied to a man …
you would see them coming in with their big…
you know these great big boots and coarse suits and you would say
‘Oh, he’s like a big [mùrlach/?].’
You know. It applied that way.
Bùrach, you don’t remember?
No, no … I didn’t think it was …
Oh, now …
Now, a bùrach of something … what was it?
Oh, gosh she … she used it often.
A bùrach.
I think I may know what you’re getting at but I don’t want to …
No, I canna tell you, Angus
but I know she used it.
What was that expression then?
No, I don’t think … no, I’m no’ getting it.
But I know she used it.
It’ll maybe come back to you.
It’s funny how the words come in to your mind just going away back.
Now you also mentioned …
Pook, pook.
Aye, to pook anything.
Oh, aye that’s Scots.  That’s to pluck.
That’s no’ Gaelic.
No, I think that’s just Scots.
Now, what about [maorach/?]?
Is that no’ what you were at already? No?
[Smeurach/?]? No, no.
Was it [smeurach/?] I said?
[Smeurach/?], aye.
Put a [smeurach/?] on it.
And what did you say the now?
Maorach. Maorach.
Maorach? No, I don’t know.
Maorach-bàn.
Is that somebody’s name?
No, it applies to shellfish.
Whelks, cooked whelks.
No?
You didn’t hear a word for
wood that was cut, peeled off to kindle a fire?
Sliseags?
No, I don’t think I heard of that …
[What about/?] the word for a bend, a bend in anything?
No.
A cam.
I only know the cams in the hoose.
What’s that?
A cam.
That’s the bus.
Is that the bus away?
No, it’s no use her standing away up there in the cold.
It’s just away round.
What was a … what was that- a cam in the hoose?
Well, is that no’ …
the cams o’ a hoose- where …
where would you say the cams …
I’ve heard you say cams.
Aye, the cams.
Is it about the fireplace, no?
I think it’s the sides o’ the fireplace.
You know, in the cams.
Oh, aye, that’s a word but …
I think it would be used the day.
I don’t know … I don’t know really …
Whether it sounds like [XX]
The cams. I think it’s the big bits that hold anything up.
Oh aye.
I don’t know though. No.
I think it would.
I’ve heard it right enough.
You didn’t hear it applied to a bend?
No.
Like a cam in a pole.
[XX] Oh, I did, Angus.
I used to hear them say ‘Oh, there’s a cam on it’.
Aye, I did.
What was that? Anything that was bent.
‘There a cam on it’.
The [sayings/?] come back to you- you’ve to think.
You didn’t hear a word [fogage/?]?
To [fogage/?] something out.
Is it to look for something?
I’m no’ sure at all. No.
It’s a word I got from Henry.
Whether he … whether he made it up or not,
I don’t know but nobody else can recognise it.
[Fogage/?]?
[Fogage/?] it out.
I took it to mean to puzzle it out.
But he doesn’t recognise it himself now.
No, I never heard it.
But of course Henry’s about eighteen years older than me.
Now, this word you mentioned beforehand …
a country person.
A yokel?
No. Oh well, it’s the equivalent.
Neònach? Well, I …
What exactly does that mean?
Well …
Simple, no?
Well when you say … no, I wouldn’t say he was simple.
He’s awful neònach. Kind of …
Glaikit?
Aye, just glaikit.
It could … you could use that word for a person that wasn’t awful well educated
or you could use it for a person that’s no awful well dressed.
[XX] He’s awful neònach looking.
You used it …
I heard you using it in that sense with a visitor we had.
Neònach?
It doesn’t matter.
No, it was somebody during the war.
No, this was on a recent visit.
He came out of his car and you said ‘He’s awful neònach’.
Och, aye. It was Bob.
But when I saw him right he wasn’t that neònach!
No. No.
You didn’t hear of a [sgeall/?] or a [steall/?]?
Aye. [Sgeallach/?], no? No.
A [sgeall/?], a [sgeall/?] of herring or fish or …
a few. Is that right?
Well it … it normally means a lot but …
Well …
A [sgeall/?].
What phrases would you have heard that in?
Is that the bus?
Well, I think I’ve heard Pappy at it.
A [sgaill/?] of anything.
I really thought that it was more for fish.
Aye, well it does mainly, well, at least in these parts.
I think it mainly has a meaning as a … as a …
I thought … though I could be wrong though but I thought it was a few.
Just a … no’ a load o’ …
How would that be pronounced?
[Sgeall/?]. [Sgeall/?].
It wasn’t [steall/?]?
Aye, a [sgeall/?] of anything.
[Sgeall/?] …
Now,
you have heard bùrach but you canna remember that?
Isn’t it funny. I canna just mind …
Aye, I’ve heard of that.
… and my mother used it often.
Bùrach.
Now, have you heard of a bòcan?
It’s a man that frightens you.
‘The bòcan will get you.’
Is that pronounced boch-an?
Aye, many’s a time they would say
‘Now just be quiet or the bòcans will get you’.
Or a bòcan.
Well, that’s what I took it to mean.
Is that what you’ve got?
Oh, well- there are a few meanings on it.
That’s one of them.
I think the dictionary definition is a hobgoblin …
something of that kind …
Oh, well maybe that just comes in something the same.
That would be applied mainly to a [XX] for children.
Och hang, I must put on my blanket.
I always forget about it because it takes an hour,
an hour and a half at times.
That word, you …
you don’t hear or use that word now, no?
What, bòcan? No, no.
Och no, the weans wouldn’t know what it meant.
But we used it.
‘There’s a bòcan out there that’ll get you.’
Now, truisealach.
Truisealach? Rubbish.
‘It’s just truis … it’s just truisealach.’
‘It’s rubbish.’
Would that be applied to anything.
Anything, aye. Anything you thought was rubbish.
Was that quite commonly used?
Angus!
Oh, aye.
I can’t get my blanket on.
Oh, heck. [XX]
Did you hear that, a word for mumps? …
Mump … mumpan, no.
You may not have used it [...]
[XX] I take it there’s a connection with the galar-plocach?
Galar-plocach?
Oh heavens.
How would you pronounce that?
Galar-plocach.
I don’t know what it is though.
That’s just mumps.
Is it!
What …
I thought I heard the name before but …
What … what use would that word have? … Words.
Galar-plocach?
Would it be a [sweary/?] name for the mumps?
Aye, but I’m just wondering what connection you heard it in?
Oh, I canna mind, Angus, no.
You just remember the word?
I just … I just remember that I …
way back in my mind that I’ve heard of it.
Familiar, but I really don’t know what it was.
What about buinneach?
Buinneach?
He would gie you the buinneach.
Anybody that …
Scunner.
Anything that you’d get fed-up wi’.
Such as this blethering.
‘Oh, you’re giving me the buinneach listening to you.’
Is that no’ right?
Scunners.
If we would be wi’ anybody that we got fed-up wi’
‘Oh that one would gie you the buinneach’.
That’s … do you hear that nowadays?
No’ so much, no, no.
But it was … when I was younger
it was a common enough saying.
‘Oh, she would gie you the buinneach’.
What about [balugran/?]?
[Balugran/?]?
I’ve heard o’ that.
I’ve heard you saying it.
[Balugran/?]? No.
[Balugran/?]. What about sùgan?
I’ve heard o’ that.
[Suigean/?]? That’s a plant …
sùgans.
You’re no’ thinking of [summons/?], no?
I thought it was …
when we were going on a picnic years ago …
before I was married,
Angus was there and somebody was saying ‘Oh, it’s going to rain,
it’s …’, ‘Och’ they said ‘You’re a sùgan’,
meaning you were putting a dampener on everything.
I’ve never heard that.
Well, that’s …
I thought really it was a plant, like a [sùrag/?].
You didn’t hear of a [gadrach/?]?
No.
[Gadrach/?]? Is that to gad aboot, no?
No. It’s more a fishing [XX]. It just means mibbe …
a [sleever/?], no?
Aye, ‘I’ll gie you a sleever.’
No, think of something else.
I think that’s more English.
Have you no’ heard of men having a sleever, a right good drink?
No.
A right sleever.
I’ve heard of that.
Oh, have you? No, I’ve never heard of that.
Was there a local name for porridge?
[Stourins/?].
[Stourins/?]?
Away!
Where did you hear that?
Well, when I …
when we were in Gayfield Place and I was only a wee lassie
Mrs Anderson, you know Barbara and Flora and them?
Their mother was next door
and she’d come oot and she’d shout
‘Come in and get your [stourins/?].
They’re lifted.’
And sometimes I’d go in and it was a plate of porridge.
But I never heard your granny say it,
it was aye porridge but that was what she called it - [stourins/?].
Must have been … used.
I’ll clour you-
wallop you but he never did it.
What was the boat that Johnny had? [Clourin/?].
Is that no’ a Gaelic name?
Aye, she came from [Carradale/?]
but I’m no’ just quite sure what that means.
What, was it the boat that came from [Carradale/?]?
Aye, I think so.
Who had it? Was it Johnny? No.
Had he the Ella? No.
[Scaff/?]
No.
[XX] the word for a pig?
[Duircean/?]
That’s just what it meant.
You’ve got a good memory.
You didn’t hear a word sàrach?
Aye
Aye, what’s that?
Wait a minute …
sàrach.
Would it mean raw? No?
‘Tastes sarach’…
I’ve heard the word.
Sour, no?
No, the usual connection it’s used in is maybe trouble.
Fishermen use it a lot [when/?] it’s sàrach.
A bit of bother … a problem.
Have you ever [heard/?] smùrach used in connection with the weather?
No’ really.
It’s smùrach the day.
It could be right enough.
A smùrach kind of day.
Oh dear knows - I just canna mind.
You never found out what [tories/?] meant?
There was this old woman that had the Gaelic
and she used to say to Bill and I,
'Oh, my, you’re a pair of tories.’
What it meant I don’t know.
No, I havna’ [XX].
Auntie Teenie used to say to Barbara ‘You wee [torie lough/?]’.
Whatever that meant I don’t know.
There’s a word … you mentioned there,
Torie lough.
[sgeochal/?]
Aye, [sgeochal/?] [Sgeochal/?]?
Aye, it’s to clear your throat.
Where did you get that word?
Auntie Tina.
She’d say ‘Stop your [sgeochling/?].’
The likes o’ me coughing like that.
I never heard o’ it.
Aye, she used to say that a lot.
Did she have Gaelic?
Aye, I don’t know.
She came from up country but …
and she would say tuirn,
tuirneaps and rùbrab, rùbrab.
Aye, Johhny’s wife aye said that too.
Is that the country?
Well, I don’t know.
Just, she used to say rùbrab,
rùbrab and tuirneap.
Tuirneap.
Aye … she always said that.
Now, you didna hear the word brash?
Oh, aye brash. Bold? No, no. No?
No, no.
No.
But, eh … rough and ready.
You know, you’re awful brash just.
No, this was [XX] …
Quick.
Like a brash. [XX] say there was a brash.
It was maybe more used at the fishing.
It just meant there was a sudden rush of [XX], you know. Now …
Well, if you say anybody’s brash …
you, if you were running out there:
‘Oh, he’s that brash.’ I’ve heard that. That’s the …
I think that’s English.
Whether the word … whether this other word brash is English too.
What about … was there a word moggans?
Aye
Aye, your moggans.
Is it a moggan of … wine, beer?
No, that’s noggin.
Noggin, oh aye. Moggans.
Is that no’ your shoes?
I used to say moggans for my wee shoes.
Shoes.
Wee [Amelia/?] used to say to my granny,
‘Can you knit me moggans?’
Aye, moggans. Wee [XX]. Wee shoes.
I’m sure that MacLellan had the nickname ‘Moggans’. Moggans.
Why was that?
That was a fisherman, Moggans.
Some o’ they MacLellans were related maybe to your grandfather, some of them.
What did you understand the word to mean?
I mean no … not used as a nickname, but in general.
I knew that it referred to slippers but then again I thought there was a plant in it.
Again, a wild plant.
Maybe I’m getting mixed up.
No, it’s slippers that I heard.
Oh, it’s slippers, aye.
Oh that’s …
I’m looking for that meaning.
You didn’t hear of moggan in any other sense?
No.
To mog something. No.
Are you familiar with the word [mùchaidh/?]?
[Mùchaidh/?]? Oh, aye.
Oh, [mùchaidh/?], aye.
A sort of [mùchaidh/?] day. A damp …
Close.
Close, aye.
Humid- that’s a better word.
Aye.
Roochlin, I don’t know but I think this is Scots.
What do you take that to mean?
‘Gie you a good roochlin.’
Aye, a good shaking or what.
Aye, rough and tumble, you know.
What about clappy doo? What was that?
Clappy doo’s a shellfish isn’t it?
Were there any names, local names for shellfish you can remember?
Shellfish that you’d eat?
[Sput/?] fish.
Aye, I think that’s just from spout.
That was the razors.
Razor fish.
You didn’t hear the word [dralag/?]?
[Dralag/?].
I think that’s more a fisherman’s term too or [XX].
I think that’s more up country.
I think that’s about it.
She was making, was it [mealan creesh/?]?
[Mealan creesh/?]?
Aye. Mealie-creesh.
What was that?
[Pasty/?] pudding we called it and mealie-creesh.
Was it no’ oatmeal, onion and something?
You put in your dripping if you had roast dripping and it lovely,
and chopped onions and then your meal a’ mixed up.
Meal, aye.
I believe that will be tasty.
[It would make you eat/?].
We used to aye make it. Duncan was awfa’ fond of it.
Aye.
His mother used to sing it to them when they were wee
‘Fhir a’ bhàta na horò eile.
I climb the mountains and scan the ocean
for thee, dear boatman in fond devotion’.
It’s a nice yin.
‘When shall I see thee? Today, tomorrow?
Oh, do not leave me in lonely sorrow’.
It’s sad.
And then they sing ‘Fhir a’ bhàta’ as the chorus.
Oh, fhir a’ … the Gaelic, aye.
Aye.
Auntie Tina used to say to Barbara ‘You hoolet.’
‘You hoolet.'
That’s an owl, that’s Scots.
Oh, that’s no Gaelic, no?
No, that’s a Scots word.
She used to [XX] like that.
I never …
when you’re young you don’t take in all these words, you know.
No, you don’t.
It’s when you look back.
I think that’s it.
No, that’s fine …
Och aye there’d be other words if you could just mind.
What was that …
was it [sarach/?]? [Sarach/?].
Aye, a [sarach/?].
I’m sure that’s something to do with the wind.
[Sarach/?] [wind/?].
A good [sarach/?] wind.
I’m nearly sure that that was a saying.
I think it would be a fresh wind, you know.
I could be wrong … but
I know the word, well I don’t know any other meaning.
[Sarach/?]. Now [brouser/?]?
[Brouser/?].
Bouncer.
Big bouncing boy.
That’s what they used to say. He’s a [brouser/?].
That’s what your dad used to …
when your granny would be carrying him out in a plaid
and this woman stayed on the high road.
She’d say ‘Can I see the baby’s legs?’
She’d to open the plaid or plaid.
He was an awfa’ big wean and …
and my mother said I’m sure he’d be twelve or twelve and a half pound.
A big boy.
That applied to a … baby.
You didn’t hear the word a ‘mush’?
Aye, mush. Aye, it’s a wild mush.
It’s just what it is.
Mix up. Like [misleach/?].
A mush would be, to me, something kind of soft and mushy.
No but I think this mix up is more a local term.
They used it at the fishing- ‘wi a mush o’ boats.’
Ochan ee. I was looking at a photograph there when I was looking for the car papers.
There’s two or three boats in the Carradale at the quay,
fishing boats you know.
I don’t know who they were or whose they were.
That word you used there ‘ochan eh’ is that …
Ochan ee
Ochan ee an ee och ’s och ’s och.
That must be … that must be a Gaelic word.
That word [railleach/?]
Is it kind of cold, no feeling.
Who would that apply to?
To anybody.
Listen, eh …
oh, no you had that word that’s kind of like it.
Now, that word [suna/?]
[Suna/?]. Well, I don’t know how it’s spelt but
I’ve heard it used often enough:
‘A wee suna’, and if your dad was here he would mind it too.
What was the other one?
‘I’ll gie you a [lunering/?], a skelp or something.
That was used, again, in childhood?
Aye. Aye, I’ve heard him saying he got a wild lunering,
so it must have meant that.
But eh …
[XX] she’s no’ that old and she could mind the … the names.
‘A wee suna’, I don’t know what that would be.
It’s no’ in any of your Gaelic …
That’s fine.
A scatterin’ o’ herring.
‘Oh, there was just a scatterin’ in it’ if they were asked
if there was much herring. ‘No, just a scaterrin.’
I think that would be English right enough.